I'd like to talk to you today about the human brain,
أريد التحدث اليوم عن دماغ الانسان
which is what we do research on at the University of California.
والذي كنا نجرب الابحاث عليه في جامعة كاليفورنيا
Just think about this problem for a second.
فكروا في هذا الامر لبرهة من الزمن
Here is a lump of flesh, about three pounds,
امامكم هنا قطعة من اللحم تزن نحو 3 باوندات
which you can hold in the palm of your hand.
والتي يُمكن حملها بين راحتي يدك
But it can contemplate the vastness of interstellar space.
ولكن يمكنها التفكير باتساع الفضاء بين النجوم
It can contemplate the meaning of infinity,
ويمكنها التفكير بالابدية
ask questions about the meaning of its own existence,
ويمكنها البحث عن معنى وجودنا
about the nature of God.
وحتى عن طبيعة الإله
And this is truly the most amazing thing in the world.
وهذه بالفعل اكثر شيء مثير في عالمنا
It's the greatest mystery confronting human beings:
انها اكبر لغز يواجه البشر منذ وجودهم
How does this all come about?
ولكن من أين آتى كل هذا ؟
Well, the brain, as you know, is made up of neurons.
حسناً , ان الدماغ كما تعلمون مكون من خلايا عصبية
We're looking at neurons here.
ونحن ننظر الى الى إحداها
There are 100 billion neurons in the adult human brain.
هنالك ما يقارب 100 مليون خلية عصبية في دماغ البالغ
And each neuron makes something like 1,000 to 10,000 contacts
وكل واحدة منها تقوم من ألف الى 10 الآف اتصال
with other neurons in the brain.
مع خلية أُخرى في الدماغ
And based on this, people have calculated
وبناءً على هذا , وجد من قام بحساب ..
that the number of permutations and combinations of brain activity
عدد التراكيب والتبديلات جراء نشاط الدماغ
exceeds the number of elementary particles in the universe.
انها تتجاوز عدد العناصر الاولية في الكون
So, how do you go about studying the brain?
ولكن كيف يمكن دراسة الدماغ ؟
One approach is to look at patients who had lesions
إحدى الطرق هي بالنظر الى المرضى الذين يملكون إعتلالات
in different part of the brain, and study changes in their behavior.
في أجزاء مختلفة من الدماغ ودراسة التغيرات الناتجة عن ذلك في تصرفاتهم
This is what I spoke about in the last TED.
وهذا ما تحدثت عنه المرة السابقة في " تيد "
Today I'll talk about a different approach,
ولكن اليوم سوف أتحدث عن طريقة أُخرى
which is to put electrodes in different parts of the brain,
وهي وضع أقطاب كهربائية في مواقع مختلفة من الدماغ
and actually record the activity of individual nerve cells in the brain.
وتسجيل نشاط تلك الخلايا العصبية الموجودة في الدماغ
Sort of eavesdrop on the activity of nerve cells in the brain.
كنوع من التنصت على نشاط الخلايا العصبية في الدماغ
Now, one recent discovery that has been made
الآن , احد أحدث الاكتشافات التي تمت
by researchers in Italy, in Parma,
بواسطة علماء في ايطاليا , في بارما تحديداً
by Giacomo Rizzolatti and his colleagues,
بواسطة " جياكومو ريزولاتي " وزملائه
is a group of neurons called mirror neurons,
هو اكتشاف مجموعة من الاعصاب تدعى "أعصاب المرايا"
which are on the front of the brain in the frontal lobes.
والتي تتواجد في مقدمة الدماغ في الفص الجبهي
Now, it turns out there are neurons
ولقد تبين أن هنالك خلايا عصبية
which are called ordinary motor command neurons in the front of the brain,
تدعى " خلايا الأوامر الحركية " في مقدمة الدماغ
which have been known for over 50 years.
وهي معلومة لنا منذ 50 عام
These neurons will fire when a person performs a specific action.
تنشط هذه الخلايا عندما يقوم الشخص بتصرف محدد ما
For example, if I do that, and reach and grab an apple,
فعلى سبيل المثال , فاذا قمت انا بالتقاط تفاحة
a motor command neuron in the front of my brain will fire.
ستنشط خلية الامر الحركي في مقدمة دماغي
If I reach out and pull an object, another neuron will fire,
وإذا قمت بمد يدي وسحب عنصر ما , ستنشط خلية أُخرى
commanding me to pull that object.
آمرتٌ إيايَّ بسحبه
These are called motor command neurons that have been known for a long time.
وهذه هي خلايا الأوامر الحركية والتي نعلمها منذ زمن طويل
But what Rizzolatti found was
ولكن ما إكتشفه " ريزولاتي "
a subset of these neurons,
هو مجموعة فرعية من هذه الاعصاب
maybe about 20 percent of them, will also fire
يما يقارب 20% منها , سوف تنشط أيضاً
when I'm looking at somebody else performing the same action.
عندما أنظُر الى شخص يقوم بنفس العمل
So, here is a neuron that fires when I reach and grab something,
أي, هذه خلية عصبية سوف تنشط عندما اقوم بإمساك عنصر ما
but it also fires when I watch Joe reaching and grabbing something.
وتلك أُخرى تنشط أيضاً عندما يقوم " جو " بنفس العمل وإمساك هذا الشيء
And this is truly astonishing.
وهذا مُذهلٌ حقاً
Because it's as though this neuron is adopting
لانه يبدو أن هذه الخلايا تعتمد
the other person's point of view.
وجهة نظر الشخص الآخر
It's almost as though it's performing a virtual reality simulation
انها كما لو أنها تؤدي محاكاة عملية لواقع
of the other person's action.
تصرف الشخص الآخر
Now, what is the significance of these mirror neurons?
والآن ما أهمية خلايا "أعصاب المرايا"
For one thing they must be involved in things like imitation and emulation.
أولا يبدو أنها تطورت للقيام بأمور مثل التقليد والمحاكاة
Because to imitate a complex act
لانه لكي تُقلد فعل مُعقد
requires my brain to adopt the other person's point of view.
يتوجب عليك أن تتبنى وجهة نظر الشخص الآخر
So, this is important for imitation and emulation.
لذا فأن تلك الخلايا مفيدة للتقليد والمحاكاة
Well, why is that important?
حسناً ولمَ هذا مُهم ؟
Well, let's take a look at the next slide.
دعونا ننظر الى الشريحة التالية
So, how do you do imitation? Why is imitation important?
إذاً , كيف يمكنك ان تُقلد ؟ ولمَ التقليد مُهم ؟
Mirror neurons and imitation, emulation.
"أعصاب المرايا" , التقليد , المحاكاة
Now, let's look at culture, the phenomenon of human culture.
الآن لننظر الى الثقافة , ظاهرة ثقافة الانسان
If you go back in time about [75,000] to 100,000 years ago,
إذا عدنا في الزمن الى نحو 75-100 الف سنة
let's look at human evolution, it turns out
وبالنظر الى تطور الانسان يتبين
that something very important happened around 75,000 years ago.
ان هنالك شيء مهم جداً حدث قبل 75 الف سنة
And that is, there is a sudden emergence and rapid spread
وهو الانتشار المُفاجىء والسريع
of a number of skills that are unique to human beings
لعدد المهارات التي يتميز بها الانسان
like tool use,
مثل استخدام الادوات
the use of fire, the use of shelters, and, of course, language,
او إشعال النار , او استخدام الملاجىء وطبعاً اللغة
and the ability to read somebody else's mind
والقدرة على قراءة ما يُفكر به الطرف الاخر
and interpret that person's behavior.
وتفسير تصرفاته
All of that happened relatively quickly.
وقد حدث هذا بسرعة كبيرة نسبياً
Even though the human brain had achieved its present size
بالرغم من أن الدماغ قد وصل الى حجمه الحالي
almost three or four hundred thousand years ago,
من ما يقارب 3-4 مئة سنة مضت
100,000 years ago all of this happened very, very quickly.
ولكن منذ 100 الف سنة حدث كل هذا بسرعة كبيرة جداً
And I claim that what happened was
وانا أدعي ان ماحدث كان بسبب
the sudden emergence of a sophisticated mirror neuron system,
الظهور المفاجىء لتلك الخلايا العصبية الفرعية المتطورة
which allowed you to emulate and imitate other people's actions.
والتي سمحت لنا بتقليد ومحاكاة أفعال الاشخاص الآخرين
So that when there was a sudden accidental discovery
أي عندما يظهر هنالك إكتشاف مفاجىء
by one member of the group, say the use of fire,
بواسطة أحد افراد المجموعة , وليكن مثلاً استعمال النار
or a particular type of tool, instead of dying out,
او استعمال إحدى الادوات , بدلاً عن الزوال
this spread rapidly, horizontally across the population,
ينتشر هذا الاكتشاف بسرعة كبيرة أُفقيا عبر أفراد الجماعة
or was transmitted vertically, down the generations.
وينتشر عاموديا عبر الاجيال القادمة
So, this made evolution suddenly Lamarckian,
وهذا ما يجعل التطور أقرب الى لامارك منه
instead of Darwinian.
الى دارون
Darwinian evolution is slow; it takes hundreds of thousands of years.
لان التطور الدارويني بطيء ويستغرق مئات الآلاف من السنين
A polar bear, to evolve a coat,
حيث لكي يطور الدب القطبي معطفاً
will take thousands of generations, maybe 100,000 years.
سيستغرق ذلك منه الالاف من الاجيال ربما 100 الف عام
A human being, a child, can just watch its parent
ولكن للبشر , عندما يراقب الطفل والده
kill another polar bear,
يقتل دباً قطبياً
and skin it and put the skin on its body, fur on the body,
ويسلخ فروته ويقوم بارتدائها على جسمه
and learn it in one step. What the polar bear
فإنه يتعلم ذلك بخطوة واحدة . أي أن الدب القطبي
took 100,000 years to learn,
يستغرق 100 الف عام لكي يتعلم ..
it can learn in five minutes, maybe 10 minutes.
ماقد يمكن تعلمه في 5 دقائق او ربما 10 دقائق لدى الانسان
And then once it's learned this it spreads
وعندما يتم تعلم هذه المهارة فإنها تنتشر
in geometric proportion across a population.
كمتتالية هندسية عبر الجماعة
This is the basis. The imitation of complex skills
هذه هي الاساسيات . فتقليد الافعال المُعقدة
is what we call culture and is the basis of civilization.
هو الذي يمكن وصفه بالثقافة وأساس التمدن والتحضر
Now there is another kind of mirror neuron,
والآن هنالك نوع آخر من تلك الخلايا العصبية الفرعية
which is involved in something quite different.
والتي تطورت في وقت مختلف
And that is, there are mirror neurons,
وهي خلايا " أعصاب المرايا "من نوع آخر
just as there are mirror neurons for action, there are mirror neurons for touch.
فكما يوجد تلك التي تُعنى بالافعال توجد تلك التي تُعنى باللمس
In other words, if somebody touches me,
بمعنى آخر عندما يقوم أحدهم بلمس ..
my hand, neuron in the somatosensory cortex
يدي , فان الاعصاب في القشرة العصبية
in the sensory region of the brain fires.
في المنطقة الحسية في الدماغ تنشط
But the same neuron, in some cases, will fire
ولكن نفس هذا العصب في بعض الحالات ينشط
when I simply watch another person being touched.
عندما أقوم ببساطة بلمس شخص آخر
So, it's empathizing the other person being touched.
اي انه تعاطف مع الطرف الاخر الذي تم لمسه !
So, most of them will fire when I'm touched
حسنا , معظم هذه الخلايا سوف تنشط عندما يتم لمسي
in different locations. Different neurons for different locations.
في مناطق مختلفة . عصب ما لكل منطقة ما
But a subset of them will fire even when I watch somebody else
ولكن الاجزاء الفرعية منها سوف تنشط أيضا عندما أُشاهد احداً ..
being touched in the same location.
يتم لمسه في نفس المنطقة
So, here again you have neurons
إذا لدينا نحن خلايا عصبية
which are enrolled in empathy.
مسؤولة عن التعاطف
Now, the question then arises: If I simply watch another person being touched,
والسؤال الذي يُطرح الان : اذا رايت شخصاً يتم لمسه
why do I not get confused and literally feel that touch sensation
لماذا لا أشعر فعليا بتلك اللمسة أو يختلط الامر علي
merely by watching somebody being touched?
أي فقط عندما أُشاهد شخصاً يتم لمسه
I mean, I empathize with that person but I don't literally feel the touch.
أعني , انا اتعاطف مع ذلك الشخص ولكن لا أشعر فعلياً بتلك اللمسة
Well, that's because you've got receptors in your skin,
حسناً هذا بسبب اننا نملك مستقبلات حسية في جلدنا
touch and pain receptors, going back into your brain
مستقبلات للالم وللمس متصلة مع الدماغ
and saying "Don't worry, you're not being touched.
تقول له " لا تقلق لم يتم لمسك انت "
So, empathize, by all means, with the other person,
لذا " تعاطف بما يعني ذلك مع الشخص الآخر
but do not actually experience the touch,
ولكن لا تتفاعل مع تلك اللمسة
otherwise you'll get confused and muddled."
وإلا سوف تصاب بالتشوش والارتباك
Okay, so there is a feedback signal
نعم . هنالك إذا اشارة تُرسل
that vetoes the signal of the mirror neuron
تقوم بعمل " فيتو " على اشارة الخلايا العصبية الفرعية
preventing you from consciously experiencing that touch.
تمنعنا من الشعور فعليا بصورة واعية بتلك اللمسة
But if you remove the arm, you simply anesthetize my arm,
ولكن اذا بترت اليد , او ببساطة خدرتها
so you put an injection into my arm,
أي قمت بحقن يدك
anesthetize the brachial plexus, so the arm is numb,
لتخدير الضفيرة العضدية لكي تصبح اليد مخدرة
and there is no sensations coming in,
أي لن يكون هنالك مستقبلات تعمل
if I now watch you being touched,
فالان اذا شاهدت أحدا يتم لمسه
I literally feel it in my hand.
فأنا فعلياً أشعر بتلك اللمسة
In other words, you have dissolved the barrier
أي بمعنى آخر لقد قمت بإزالة الحاجز
between you and other human beings.
بينك وبين الأفراد الآخرين
So, I call them Gandhi neurons, or empathy neurons.
لذا فأنا ادعوهم " خلايا غاندي " او " خلايا التعاطف "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And this is not in some abstract metaphorical sense.
وهذا ليس مجرد تعبير مجازي
All that's separating you from him,
فأن كل ما يفصلك عن ..
from the other person, is your skin.
الشخص الآخر هو جلدك
Remove the skin, you experience that person's touch in your mind.
أزل هذا الجلد وسوف تشعر بتلك اللمسة في دماغك
You've dissolved the barrier between you and other human beings.
فأنت بهذا قمت بإزالة الحواجز بينك وبين الأفراد الآخرين
And this, of course, is the basis of much of Eastern philosophy,
وهذا حتما هو أساس الفلسفة الغربية
and that is there is no real independent self,
أي انه لايوجد ما يسمى الاستقلال الفردي التام
aloof from other human beings, inspecting the world,
عن البشر من حلولنا , بالنظر الى العالم
inspecting other people.
وبالنظر الى الاشخاص
You are, in fact, connected not just via Facebook and Internet,
فأنت بالحقيقة متصل معهم ليس فقط عبر " الفيس بوك " او الانترنت
you're actually quite literally connected by your neurons.
انما أيضاً عبر الخلايا العصبية بصورة فعلية نوعا ما
And there is whole chains of neurons around this room, talking to each other.
والآن يوجد العديد من الاتصالات بين الخلايا العصبية في هذه الغرفة تتحدث مع بعضها
And there is no real distinctiveness
ولا يوجد اي فرق حقيقي بين
of your consciousness from somebody else's consciousness.
وعيك الشخصي عن وعي الشخص الآخر
And this is not mumbo-jumbo philosophy.
وهذه ليست فلسفة " فارغة "
It emerges from our understanding of basic neuroscience.
فلقد اتضحت من خلال فهمنا لاساسيات علم الأعصاب
So, you have a patient with a phantom limb. If the arm has been removed
لانه عندما تملك مريضا لديه يد وهمية نتجت بعد بتر يده الاصلية
and you have a phantom, and you watch somebody else
أي عندما تملك يداً وهمية وشاهدت شخصاً آخر
being touched, you feel it in your phantom.
يتم لمسه , سوف تشعر بها بيدك الوهمية
Now the astonishing thing is,
والامر المذهل في هذا
if you have pain in your phantom limb, you squeeze the other person's hand,
أنه ان كنت تشعر بألم في يدك الوهمية .وقمت بتدليك يد الشخص الآخر
massage the other person's hand,
وعمل مساج لتلك اليد
that relieves the pain in your phantom hand,
فإن هذا سيحرر الألم في يدك الوهمية
almost as though the neuron
أي تشعر الخلايا العصبية
were obtaining relief from merely
بالتحرر من الألم بمجرد
watching somebody else being massaged.
النظر الى شخص آخر يتم تدليكه
So, here you have my last slide.
وهذه هي الشريحة النهائية
For the longest time people have regarded science
لمدة طويلة من الزمن العلم و ..
and humanities as being distinct.
الانسانية أمران منفصلان
C.P. Snow spoke of the two cultures:
" سي بي . سنو " تحدث عن الثقافتين
science on the one hand, humanities on the other;
العلم كأحدى اليدين , والانسانية هي الأُخرى
never the twain shall meet.
لا يجب أن تجتمعا
So, I'm saying the mirror neuron system underlies the interface
وأنا أقول ان تلك الخلايا العصبية الفرعية تحمل وجهة نظر
allowing you to rethink about issues like consciousness,
تجعلنا نعيد تفكيرنا بأُمور مثل الوعي
representation of self,
وتمثيل الذات
what separates you from other human beings,
و ما يفرقنا عن الاشخاص الاخرين
what allows you to empathize with other human beings,
وما يجمعنا معهم ويجعلنا نتعاطف معهم
and also even things like the emergence of culture and civilization,
وأيضاً فيما يخص ظهور الحضارة والثقافة
which is unique to human beings. Thank you.
التي جعلتنا متميزين كبشر , شُكراً
(Applause)
( تصفيق )